Hello friends, I am Pankaj Mathpal
CPW and welcome to our
new episode. We will talk
about Arogya Sanjivani. Arogya Sanjivani
is a health insurance policy. IRDA had
instructed all the insurance companies, i.e., health insurance companies and general insurance companies, that they will again
launch a health insurance policy with standard terms and conditions. They should decide that this will be an
insurance policy which the
policy holder does not face any problem in understanding.
Recently, IRDA made some more changes in it. Actually, the
minimum sum insured in this insurance policy was ₹1 and the
maximum sum insured could be made up to ₹500.
But recently,
it has told the insurance companies that they can
take a sum insured of less than 1 lakh in it, which
means that policy holders can take this
policy with a sum insured of less than 1 lakh
and it can be more than the mentioned in
steel pipe leg. So,
today we will discuss this, but before that
I would request you once again that
if you have not yet subscribed to our YouTube channel, then
definitely
subscribe to it and also press the bell icon.
Friends, this policy is as
I told you that all the insurance companies will
launch this policy with the same terms and conditions. The
premium of this policy may differ from one insurance company to another.
An insurance company will
keep the same premium for this policy. It is
easy to understand this because once you
know the terms and conditions, then
you can understand that you will prefer any company
whose premium is lower
because the terms and conditions are different. Secondly,
whenever you
want to support this, then if
you are folding the policy which you are currently in, then it may be
that the terms and conditions of the health insurance policy of another insurance company are
different. But if you have
bought the Arogya Sanjeevani policy from one insurance company and in the feature you want to
code it in another insurance company, then
because that insurance company
also has the policy  Its terms and
conditions will be framed, so it will be
easy for you to opt for it. This policy is
Arogya Sanjivani. Any person between the age of 18 to
65 years can take it.
It can be availed
as an individual or family floater.
Dependent children from 3 months to 25 years can be
covered under this policy along with the parents. In this policy,
as in any health insurance policy, there will be
a waiting period. If you
take the policy, then in the first thirty days, no other
plan except accident will be
accepted. Hospitalization of the required charge
is necessary. If there is a minimum
charge for addition, then you
can do it. Other health insurance
policies also have such conditions. This policy
is a policy, instead of annual mode, it can be either early or half
yearly and this
policy will be a one-year policy. The
biggest thing is that there will be
sub-limits in the Arogya Sanjivani policy, that is,
your policy comes for Phase-5 and
above.  Also, here the
rule which will be four judges, there is CAT, that is
per cent of the sum insured and maximum ₹5000,
so if your room rent is more than 500
then you will have to share it from your pocket,
apart from this, here KO means when you have to
spend five percent from your pocket, similarly for
sure charges, you will have to wait for the subscription or
use of this cream,
other insurance
policies are about that,
in some insurance companies there the
waiting period is after thirty-six months
and in some insurance companies the
waiting period may be of sixty months
but by paying a little extra premium
you can reduce that waiting period from sixty months to
12 months also,
you will not get this facility in Sanjeevani of this charge, according to
me, nowadays in the health insurance
policy you get multiple
benefits, that is, in any claim
premium, that is, if you have taken a policy
and you have not made any claim in the premium, then
next year whatever your sum is  The sum insured will
increase by 50%. See, if you have
taken a policy with a sum insured of ₹500, then the
premium will become 7.5% next year and if you do
not make any claim in the next year as well, then the
sum insured will increase by 50%, that is, it will become
₹10. So,
your sum insured can be up to double the maximum sum
insured, but
this is not possible in Arogya Sanjivani. Here, the
only bonus is 5% of the
term insurance
and the minimum is 50% of the sum insured of the
policy. So, if you have taken a policy of ₹500 and
its replacement is pending, then by adding
5% for your pain premium, you can
collect a maximum flat bonus of ₹5000. So, this is a pimples delimitation.
Apart from that, nowadays, in the new health
insurance policies, there is
a very good feature of restore real food, that is,
if you have taken a policy of ₹500  If you have taken a health insurance
policy and due to some reason the
entire sum insured of the phablet gets exhausted in one policy year
and suppose in the same policy year
after a few days you will need an airplane again, then for
any other disease except the one for which you had taken an airplane earlier,
you will get the same sum insured again
because there is a veto benefit there, that is, the
sum insured will be restored
if the entire sum is exhausted once,
but this feature is not there in Arogya Sanjivani
and there is also a condition here, IRDA has
said that no value added
services can be provided here, this
insurance policy will be launched with basic facilities only,
so this will be the same condition across the insurance
companies, the basic conditions that
I will take are those,
you will not get such conditions here, in
today's new insurance plan
you get many other benefits,
if you are talking about this Arogya Sanjivani
with any insurance company and the
same insurance  If you
look at another plan of the company instead of Arogya Sanjivani, then it is
possible that you may also be getting the benefit of a room back there.
Some insurance
plans have a feature that if you
remain active, you do any
activity like walking, jogging, running, sitting, etc., then you
get reward points for that.
You can also use those reward points and for the
facilities which are not available in the previous policy, for
example, if there is OPD cover, then
you can use those reward points for OPD cover
or
if you do not have such a query, then
you can use those reward points for subscription or renewal premium.
You may get this feature in other plans
but you will not get this feature in Arogya Sanjivani.
For this,
you will have to face many limitations in Arogya Sanjivani.
If Arogya
Sanjivani is not suitable for your age, then there is not much difference in the premium
between other health insurance policies.
You should share the cover with any other PAN instead of Arogya Sanjivani.
Here you have to
play all these limits in such a way that you do not
get any limitations. Friends, if you liked the information then do
not forget to like this video and also
circulate it as much as possible among your friends and in whatever WhatsApp group you are in so that
maximum number of people
get information about it and also if you have
not subscribed to our YouTube channel yet then
subscribe to it as well and
press the bell icon. We will meet
you again with similar important information. Till then take
care of yourself.
Jai Hind Jai